hey all, it'sPprofessor Dave, I want to
continue talking about elimination reactions
specifically the E1 reaction.
so the E1 reaction is to the E2 reaction
as the SN1 reaction is to the SN2 reaction
so basically as you'd expect, the E1
reaction is going to be
two steps with a unimolecular transition state
just like with the SN1
the first step in the E1 reaction is
that the leaving group leaves
so let's take a look at this substrate
here the bromine is gonna leave
that leaves a tertiary carbocation,
now it's very very important to understand
that while this substrate, this carbon is
sp3 hybridized and therefore has
tetrahedral geometry
anytime a carbon that is sp3 hybridized
loses an electron domain, because
this bromine is leaving
with the electrons in that bond now this
carbon atom has only
three electron domains and anything surrounded by three electron domains will
exhibit trigonal planar geometry so it
is the case that this methyl group is now
flat in the board, this is now a flat
molecule with respect to the carbons
so there is a formal positive charge now
and so that means even a weak nucleophile like water can go ahead do an
acid-base reaction
and grab that proton, so here is oxygen
interacting with this proton and then
the electrons in this carbon-hydrogen
bond are the ones that go to form
the carbon-carbon pi bond in the product
thanks for watching, guys. subscribe to my
channel for more tutorials
and as always feel free to email me with questions